all right welcome James we're recording
on YouTube now yeah thanks I'm ill thank
you
and so you what weather is your interest
in reaching out to me for a conversation
what is it you're doing in this space
yeah I think it's like I kind of ended
up watching a few of the idea cafes
where like a bunch of them now I've been
following the game bSpace and some of
those kinds of communities for a while
and I've been like personally just
really interested in the kind of the
idea of a global tech operative the kid
like I feel like you could just solve so
many different problems and I've been
kind of like writing about it and
working on a kind of a side project
which is you know very much related to
that and yeah it kind of came across the
the document that you've written about
together Tech and I kind of heard you
mentioning a global tech cooperative and
some of your conversations and it just
fit I like my sense was that you kind of
locked on to the same idea that I've
been very interested in and to be honest
like I haven't found that many other
people that have kind of like locked on
to that idea and I've been kind of
sharing it when I've had opportunities
sharing ideas around that kind of
concept in some of these kind of these
change-making communities and even in
those communities I found that there's
been you know a huge amount of interest
or there's been a little bit of interest
but it doesn't seem like large numbers
of people have kind of got on board with
that with that kind of concept so yeah
it was cool to kind of come across you
that you're very interesting the same
kind of thing and I think you're the
kind of philosophy and the ideas you're
presenting it very much like in
resonance with where I'm coming from so
I just thought it'd be interesting to
have a conversation
Haizi yes I also find talking about a
global cooperative for a few years and
even switch handshake okay fine global
tech cooperative like you can get behind
the tech part right like we all own
Google we
Facebook that's a piece you can get
behind and no people don't see the
vision they either kind of want no
technology like Facebook and Google or
the devil and we need to get rid of them
completely and like what and go back to
what like no internet that's not
happening or they're like right create
it and then we'll come onboard I'm like
that's not the vision the vision is we
have to create it together otherwise it
has all the same pitfalls as everything
else like it's like a week if I have to
create it themself or so I can't I can't
code and I don't have the money to go to
it but even if I could if I won the
lottery and did that then I have to sell
it to you then you don't get to decide
what's in it the point is to have
technology that we own together and can
improve together and technology can give
us it's not the end-all be-all it
doesn't create utopia but creates the
infrastructure for us to be able to do
things at every level individually it
can improve our lives in our collective
that can improve our lives and globally
it can definitely improve our lives for
able to have that data and information
so yes it is nice to talk to someone who
shares that that vision so if you like
how many have you found many other
people that you feel like have kind of
got that same concept and they were
interested in it or do you feel like
you're kind of still on your own like I
obviously there's a lot of people that
you're talking with who I guess are
interested in kind of similar kinds of
things I know for me like I was he's
probably back in I think it was like at
the end of 2011 which seems like
absolutely ages ago now that I felt like
the I first kind of got that idea and it
came after years and years of kind of
searching and trying to understand like
what was coming next in human history
and looking at all these different areas
like economics and politics and social
networks when the idea kind of came
together that you could have this you
know for me like I feel like it would it
would start with like a social network
because I feel like there's a bunch of
stuff about a social network this unique
compared to other types of companies you
know like the ability to kind of harness
the input of lots of different people to
enable them to coordinate to make
decisions and to kind of harness
collective intelligence but once you've
got that capacity that you could then
actually start as a
company expand and kind of start funding
ventures in different kinds of markets
and gradually grow this kind of
conglomerate system which as it gets
larger and more powerful it becomes
capable of expanding more and you know
you can increase the amount of
experimentation around different types
of governance and all kinds of things
and I think yeah once that idea like
dawned on me it was just like Isis for
me it felt like that was what I've been
looking for for ages and I've kind of
never ever since then that's just been
in my mind like that's what it is you
know I still just got a very limited
individuals perspective on it but I'm
just certain that that is the solutions
are the biggest problems were facing
yeah so I had yeah wait like how did you
come to that conclusion that I don't
even remember it feels like it was just
always there and also of course not
because it's continually evolving as
well I did a dislike hippie business
course called groundswell here in
Vancouver which was amazing and every
weekend is like you come up with like a
social enterprise during it and every
weekend I would come back and like be
like I pivoted I smoked a joint and got
this new epiphany and got this new thing
and everything was generally based on
tech it was like an IMDB for politicians
and a history thing Wow
my brain is I've been on zoom' for way
too long a like a way to envision
history and zoom in and out throat
throat time and space and to do in the
beginning it was a lot of intellectual
stuff it was like how do we make sense
of the worlds and how do we what is the
data I want to have access to I have a
lot of health challenges and there's no
solutions in our current medical system
nor am i dying I don't have like a you
know not looking for the solution
because I'm gonna die in five years but
it's really frustrating to not be able
to get your health it's at its optimal
peak because you need other people you
need the data from other people you need
to know and so to see the what we can do
together that honestly no technology
company can do
it's like technology's powerful we all
get it we're on it constantly but it's
also the
industry that we could collectively own
like we the railroads the internet all
of these things would be really hard to
have owned collectively and figure out
how to do that but it wouldn't be that
hard for 10,000 people to create a
social network overnight no keed not
overnight but in six months right to
create something that they want to use
and then make it in a way that you're
continually improving it and inviting
more people on but finding those people
finding is like I was live I actually
had my first live board meeting when it
was just me in September
the day I encountered game B I was like
I gotta jump off the zoom call because
I'd have this live thing that nobody
showed up to and then within two months
of doing that
Bentley joins and then we were live for
a couple times and most of the time it's
zero people watching and then my brother
joined it known as kind of joined so
were at least more of us working through
the problems and now we're doing
solution Racing's on Saturday chart know
if you can come to 2 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time tomorrow we're talking
about food we're only on our second one
and the idea is in an hour we're able to
come up with a solution not a solution
we're actually gonna run with but if
four people or 5 people talking about a
problem can come up with a tangible
solution not the solution right so far
and we're talking about food we're not
going to end food scarcity for everybody
but if we could come up with a possible
solution for 10,000 people with $100,000
those are possible solutions like 10,000
people putting in 10 dollars isn't gonna
break the bank for the individual it's
not looking and see you don't even this
ten dollars isn't gonna feed you for the
rest of your life it's gonna help you
have more access to food right at a
cheaper level whether that means money
or resources like time that like there
are so many solutions we can create
together and anytime anyone comes up
with an idea they have to work through
all of this like BS to get it out into
the world and even then 9 out of 10 of
them fail and like if we can deal with
the foundational problems of marketing
and finance for each individual problem
that he and including for not just tech
and not just together tech but for
artists and teachers and if we can
figure out how to get our basic needs
met together then we don't need to have
jobs outside right we don't need to have
to worry about
I am a witch everyone has to do right
now in order to be co-creating game B we
can actually and I don't think it
happens at all with a flip of a switch
it's like incrementally we incrementally
make people's lives better so they can
show up more so that they can help make
other people's lives better and ends
dealing with the and so I don't even
know if answered your question James
that I came to it and it's still
evolving constantly because it's like
all of these instrument pieces of like
the tech and the people and the process
and I'm not it's not something that I
can fail at because it's not gonna be
something that stops until it exists in
the world like it's like okay does it
matter how many times it breaks or how
many times people don't show up
whoever's there we're gonna figure it
out and move forward and then break it
and figure it out and move forward yeah
yeah and I think all of these little
steps are you know that it's in
aggregate they're kind of accumulate to
be the gradual transformation I think
yeah we need all those kind of little
experimentations and discussions around
different things and it's impossible to
know what the kind of the effects are
but I think especially in the case like
with you putting everything online as
well you know those ideas are seeding
out to different people and you know I
guess you'll never know who will reach
up until now where I've kind of come on
it like I've been watching for a little
while and I've found it really
interesting and yeah I've appreciated
the ideas that you shared and other
people shared on the on the channel but
they'll never know that I appreciate
that and that might have influenced some
of my ideas and yeah so it's yeah I
think that's very important and you are
you interested like one aspect of of
this life been quite interesting for a
while is like the concept of mapping
ideas to kind of you think about how to
explain it like I guess with like the
food thing for example you could ideas
could kind of like you might someone in
the group might come up with an idea and
could put it out there but I think a lot
of times in these kind of Commerce in
these communities like the game be
community you see ideas popping up but
then they kind of just because of the
design they end up getting lost again
they kind of sink down outside and it's
it's not that that was you know it's
still valuable like it will have
impacted certain people but I feel like
that we
have we could develop tools or use
existing tools to actually kind of start
mapping those ideas onto something that
can grow and evolve over time so like
this there's an article ever written
about the kind of a concept called I've
called knowledge mapping which is
enabling communities to or group to
people you know distributed to to evolve
ideas and I think it's there's actually
kind of like similar dynamics in our
brain where you know if you think about
like there's all these different neurons
and each of them is kind of processing
little bits of information but
collaboratively they evolve you know
complex models over time and it's not
like one neuron isn't able to hold that
whole mall but it might spark a process
of thinking that then evolves a kind of
a model and yeah so like one one thing
that I'm kind of interested in this is
mapping this idea of a global tech
cooperative like one of the different
areas within that that needs to be
explored and that we need to kind of
evolve a more detailed resolution in our
understanding of so like you know
governance would be one area funding
would be another area you know there's
all these different areas but taking an
approach of map and you can kind of
start off and just say okay governance
is one thing you could make a little
note for that or a little area for that
and then within that other people can go
in and they can share little ideas and
then other people can look at those
ideas and they can add a little bit more
on and gradually at a time you get this
kind of evolving map that increases in
detail and and depth so yeah yeah no I
mean I think both the visualization of
information is very important to you
which is why I want all this stuff to be
out there I have sat in my room and come
up with the solute the solution for all
of those things right the funding the
governance all of this stuff for the
technology cooperative and then came to
the realization over a year ago that
before I even encounter game B like that
doesn't work because then I have to sell
it to people and I actually can't even
communicate the whole picture so how
would I sell it to anyone so instead
it's about
like bringing the people together to
have those discussions right I have at
least one option for governance and one
option for funding right but it's like
well there's pros and cons to everything
so what would be the best and then it's
also gonna be different based on do we
have four people or do we have a
thousand people and mine most of my
ideas are more designed for the ten
thousand a thousand to ten thousand
people they're not designed for the
floor but for it's not like that's easy
yeah I mean like having a conversation
to come into a consensus with four
people isn't rocket science even if
there is still interpersonal dynamics
and stuff that can make it a little
difficult but having like the people
come together to to do that but in order
for that to happen I do think that needs
to be mapped out a little better right
like these are the areas we need to talk
about right the governance the finance
and then having ways for people to have
that conversation that isn't what
currently is done which I don't know how
you're envisioning it to me but like a
forum right like a forum to me just
isn't I don't want to participate in a
forum I don't want to like come in and
add something and have to read everyone
else's stuff I can't even read it's one
of the reasons I didn't read all the
other stuff is it doesn't stick in my
brain like it used to and so what works
for me is a conversation and so what
I've the idea cafe was supposed to be a
platform that looked like the YouTube
channel does right we're forward for
people come together spend a half an
hour to an hour answering a question and
then you switch tables and either answer
the same question or built-on question
and it's creating different like that's
not even governance this governance is
like how the tech company would be run
right whereas how a decision making
process happens right how we actually
get an idea out into the world how we do
project management right like how even
if we have this thing we want to create
how do we then actually create it how do
we then decide and who gets paid for
what and what is volunteer and what is
isn't something that like one person can
decide on and then and then dictate it
to everyone else because then they have
to dictate it to everyone else there's
already that problem whereas if we can
design that together right you like hey
if you're putting in an hour a week no
you're not gonna pay for it but if
you're putting in you know like six
hours or this is your passion this is
like I mean for me it's weird because I
don't I both feel like I'm doing this
24/7 and I'm not doing it at all like
it's like oh this is when you find your
genius in your passion you don't need to
get paid for it and you
just do it naturally all day every day
and so I don't even know how I would get
paid for it because I'm like what am i
working what am I not working to see me
as doing this but at the same time if
everyone else was like no you need to
actually Bank your time and I'd figure
it out I'd be like okay when I'm in a
meeting maybe that counts or that
doesn't does this count right or it is
only the board meeting count I don't
know I don't care that's game a I don't
care about getting money for my time I
care about creating a better world but I
do need to eat yeah well one idea that
I've discussed with a few friends around
this kind of subject of like how do you
how do you allocate resources and like
fun people to contribute to the building
of this kind of a system and I think
like I'm really interested in the idea
of like giving people the tools such as
very easily tip each other for you know
any kind of contribution in a social
network but another side of it is also
creating like what I've kind of called
like crowdfunded bounty rewards so I
kind of tended to imagine this in the
context of web development like an
open-source web development project
where there's a user base that's this
large and there's there's lots of people
who say for example want a new feature
bill and they can you know anyone within
that community can put forward an idea
they could say hey we could be amazing
if we had this feature and then other
people can comment on that they can
start to kind of accumulate information
around that maybe links to other
relevant bits of information and then as
as as it got enough support you could
kind of have a almost like a dynamic
threshold depending on how large the
community was but once a certain amount
of people had showed that they were
interested in that idea it could then go
to some kind of like member vote and
then if it was accepted by the members
and it was like I've kind of imagined
this also involving a kind of a
community Constitution a co-authored
Constitution which would have certain
boundaries but let's say that it was
like across the threshold of being the
user base we're interested in it passes
the criteria of the Constitution then it
becomes like an official task and once
it's there then you kind of all the
information about the task is gathered
in one place and people can start to
then tip money to that
ask it can almost like crowd fund money
towards it the more money that starts to
accumulate around the task the greater
the incentive developers for example to
come in and say hey I'll do that task
for that you know if I can get that
bounty rewarded in return I'll take on
that task I'll do it and if there was
like you know if there's a really big
task and if the money that had been
raised for it was was significant than
you would expect that there might even
be lots of developers and lots of people
wanting to kind of compete to complete
that task and then there could be
processes where it's decided who's best
suited to complete that and then it can
be a kind of a process of review as it
gets worked on but I think that kind of
dynamic is really interesting to me like
how communities can come up with ideas
and they can create incentives and that
can it's almost like to me like the you
know the dynamics in capitalism where
where there's like an interest for
something and there's money available
for it then you start getting people
building companies around those things
and evolving ways of providing services
to meet those but this is kind of a way
that you can harness those dynamics but
within a kind of open source community
collaborative platform so I think that
kind of thing will be awesome and you
know like the kind of stuff that you're
doing at the moment I'm sure would be
seen as valuable and there would be you
know people could tip that and yes I
think that kind of a system is I think
is very possible I think one of the
things at the moment is just is just
getting the technology there so I hadn't
feel like this is one of the steps at
the moment it's just building that kind
of like seed social network that's got
enough of the features in play
oh hello by myself oh no you popped out
but then when you popped in I didn't
have to add you you were it was like
close enough I guess that is just that's
interesting
yeah I was here they um for me like I am
I come for a resource-based economy
background like that's what my vision
for the future is so a lot of what I've
designed is absolutely not designed
around trading time for money or doing
it in a way that paid for it
but if that's what incentivizes most
people that's what they need to be in
place in order for the work to get done
then I have zero problem not being the
thing that generates it my problem with
something like tipping is that I don't
know if anyone would see value in what
I'm doing and I don't be enough from an
egotistical I need money give me money
way but like it's very easy to be like
oh you coded that thing right that that
clearly is like I can see the tangible
thing whereas like emotional support or
other things like the artistic
contributions things aren't necessarily
marked like we don't necessarily think
of them as I was monetizing them because
they're not seen as in the same way and
at the same time then were incentivized
to pick the thing that's going to be
that's gonna give us the most money
instead of what what do I want to do so
my visions a little more on this side of
like doing volunteer work as much as
possible until stuff doesn't get done
and then you stand centralized for it
and that doesn't mean that's the right
way just that like I for me like I said
I do this for free right like I'm like
this is I can't pay me not to do this
think if Google was like awesome I'll
give you a million dollars don't create
your tech cooperative and that wouldn't
happen yeah you like I'm like this is
aimed in and of itself and I think the
more were able to tap into that I have
this paper somewhere that showcases like
how to get a task done it's like well if
one person knows about the task can do
the task they have the skills for and
wants to do the task then they're in the
sweet spot you don't need to pay them
the issue is our entire economy is based
on people who know how to do the tasks
know the task needs to get done it
doesn't want to do the task so we pay
them and the other one of course if you
don't know how to do it you can get
trained and the biggest loss piece is
all the people who know how to do the
task and want to do the task but in no
way no it needs to get done
that's just a database right I'm like
hey this pothole needs to get filled
this logo needs to get made and putting
it out to the community with zero token
zero you know like maybe you can see how
much you've contributed but you're not
getting paid to contribute until late
this logo has been here for three weeks
and no one's done it right so why
doesn't this work getting done and then
finding ways to incentivize it beyond
money just because of the incentives
that come with money in my mind is very
gaming I don't know how to get around
that with the tokens but I like gamify
and I like you like all this stuff
around that so if that is again what
would work to get people on board to do
it I like the idea of voting on the
things that are most important the issue
is then like my vision for like we
brainstorm the like the features we
would want in it kind of design the beta
together and then pay someone to make it
right and so it's probably like a tech
team the bids on it or or again they do
it for free when they're like not
necessarily the actual
full-time work what they do for free but
if you have dozens of tech teams
competing for it where they're like hey
here's what this would look like to us
this is what it would look to us and we
vote on which one we look the best who
can do it for that price point and then
both their staffs kept on that team
where it's like wait you said you could
do it for a hundred thousand and you're
at a million that's not within budget at
all or we're just sorry you can only get
a hundred thousand only if you you
actually finish it but if I anyways like
nothing is the end-all be-all
right it's like finding ways to tweak it
as we go like this is is the work
getting done or the project good is it
how do we have a pool of money like my
vision was and again we're creating from
the ground up so everyone gets to bring
their ideas we get to figure out what's
the what what are the pros and cons of
each method was to have a catalog of
apps that is worth and for people to put
ten dollars a month into and and you
have theoretically tens of thousands
hundreds of thousands of members putting
ten dollars a month into something that
and the only reason when you had said
about company is starting themselves
right around that is like that doesn't
in my minds outcompetes game like like
Google can out-compete that Facebook can
open that but having an umbrella
corporation where you don't have to do
the HR you don't have to write
company you can just run the idea right
it's like I have the idea can I find a
team around it can i how do we continue
forward with it how do we make the thing
into the world that the most efficiency
possible and some time might be from
especially legal reasons in game a to
have its own company right and then
other way like no this doesn't need to
be a company yet or doesn't ever need to
be a company and working through that
whole process is also a tech it's like
do we add on to like if I come up with
an idea that is something that could be
part of your app right and you own that
up how do I get it to be part of yours
because I don't want it like part of
this is as a user as someone who uses
apps
I don't want 50,000 apps on my phone and
I want container communicate with each
other and looking from that foundation
of how do we make tech the most powerful
and the least risky and have people kind
of there to support it as opposed to
although right now we are kind of down
this path I don't necessarily care about
getting a tech person's idea made into
the world I care about the idea being in
the world so the members can you so the
users can use it right like that's
actually is that is the baby is the
thing that changes the world that helps
is the actual service that it's doing
and so how can the best service out
there for our members and right now that
probably looks like buying them and or
either creating them from scratch which
is my vision or buying what already
exists right which we have no money to
buy them but at the same time if 10,000
people came together and put $10 into a
pot we could buy it a out somewhere
broader does know this I'm sure it's a
fee the ones that have already went
bankrupt but they are still someone's
intellectual property right the same
thing that got built again and again and
again and then went under is anyway yeah
you know I totally agree and like going
back to what you were saying earlier I I
think it's I think you're right that
like my kind of vision of an ideal
society is not where everyone is
motivated by money and I think this kind
of like this creating incentives is
useful but I think you want a society
where there's enough abundance that
people can basically be free to follow
their passions and you know I'm in the
same boat where like I've put an
enormous amount of effort into this kind
of stuff for years
probably lost money overall or
definitely have I've not gained any
money from it so but I love doing it you
know it's like it's my passion so that's
that's what I'm interested in as long as
I'm like getting by okay you know I'm
pretty content I'm not after not half
the money but at the same time there are
situations where there's like something
that unloaded people really need done
and maybe they haven't got the skills to
do it and if there's a way that they can
kind of like it could be coordinated
through crowdfunding and there's kind of
like a process in place where there's
kind of a little battle of natural
selection where the people who are most
adapt for meeting that need are kind of
selected and are then able to perform
that function for the collective I think
that's what's really valuable as well
and on one of your later points like I
think I'm quite interested in I my
inclination is that I think we should I
think we will need to actually build the
tech like I think the idea of kind of
like buying other things other apps
would come with certain disadvantages
like I think if you if you build this
platform from the ground up and it's
like if if people think through it
really clearly like how the database is
organized
I think loads of these different apps
like you're saying are actually really
interoperable and you get a lot of
advantages by having them integrated
within one system and you know there's
there's a lot of people that are very
afraid about that like this idea of kind
of centralization and so you know
companies like Google and Amazon and
stuff it's understandably I think
there's a healthy fear about that
because you get a huge amount of power
with that centralization and if the
ownership structure is kind of
dictatorial and opaque that's a really
dangerous thing but if you're able to
have that system and it's transparent
and it's got you know distributed power
and there's huge amount of participation
involved you can kind of harness those
advantages that come with centralization
without with while avoiding the
disadvantages and I think it right like
what we want is a kind of like a future
like Facebook Google Amazon
that's like owned by everyone and it's
got all the different features that you
need and there's just a continuously
evolving ecosystem
of different apps and tools that are
evolving within it and yeah that's just
I think there's a huge amount of power
that could that could be imation with
that yeah absolutely and I agree that I
think that designing them from the
ground up together so they can
interconnect with each other it makes
more sense but where we're starting
right now is that like the missions kind
of like the Netflix of apps right so the
customer is paying $10 to get it to get
a catalog of apps which right now is
each one is its own individual thing on
your phone right so if instead of paying
$10 a month for your food one and $10
one for your finance one and ten dollars
a month for the one that's your personal
trainer we've went and decided what are
the best ones and hopefully we own the
best one and so for your $10 a month
instead of $10 to each of them you get
access to all of them
the beauty about if that is the method
that we choose to go forward with this
unlike Netflix and it does vote they
have licensed content right which is
most of their content then they have
their own into the content that they've
created that's always going to be there
like stranger things and stuff the
difference is Netflix can't knock off
frozen right they can't knock off
diehard
no one's gonna watch the knockoff
version it has to be the actual movie
whereas we can write we can be like oh
no one would sell us their app for a
hundred thousand dollars under the food
umbrella so we're gonna create our own
and it probably makes more sense to
create our own anyway but if we want a
catalog we're not going to be able to
create everything all at once so it's
like okay well what's the best that's
out there and what does it make the most
sense to move on with next right what
apps exist right because apps exist in
all of these spaces mostly then are
amazing and do help your life but
they're not interconnected with each
other and you don't own them when we
can't improve them and so having the
catalog but yeah with the understanding
that one if you're not gonna sell it to
us and we're not gonna own it so that we
can talk if you have the data talk to
each other and then yeah we're just
gonna create one from the ground up we
can recreate our frozen and our diehards
and our Star Wars part of it it's what
Google and Facebook do right it's like
oh we'll buy you oh we can't buy you
great we'll just recreate a competing
one and we got all the marketing and all
people so we win we're doing that
reverse it's like okay
sorry not sorry the people need people
need food the people need education that
we believe and we can create the
technology that gives us yeah and is
there's also like as I've kind of
because up until about a year ago I was
you know I was like invite like I don't
know if you've seen this this website we
Co which is kind of it's like a an
open-source social network project that
I've been involved in which has been my
kind of like experimentation with these
kinds of ideas and but I had been a
coder myself up until about a year ago
where I finally was just like I need to
learn this stuff like I wasn't really
enjoying the job I was in so I've in the
last year I've been like learning as
much as I can and it's been really
rewarding and I feel like my perspective
on like what needs to be done has
developed quite a bit but there's a huge
amount of common common common ality
between all the different apps that you
see out there so like one thing that I
be I could share with you after the call
if you're interested is I've been
creating a kind of like a database map
of because I've started kind of
recreating wiko myself now just kind of
rebuilding it kind of as a learning
experiment but it also it's in an old
framework at the moment so it kind of
needs rebuilding anyway but I've been
getting into now like the database
design and creating like you know user
databases and community databases and
then linking them up and kind of
visualizing the relationships between
these different tables but yeah I'd be
happy to share that with you because I'd
be interested in like what some of the
different app ideas you have are and
like what would be required in terms of
like the information in the database but
yeah I think like we could you know you
can have this this kind of transparent
map so everyone can see exactly how data
is being stored how its organized and
then also that would it would make it
easier for other developers who wanted
you know to develop a new tool instead
of having to build the whole database
and the user accounts and all these
different things it's that's already
there all they need to do is the surface
features yeah exactly
I mean that is like a common data pool
that's both like data data sorry like
you know information on corporate on
corporations information
products information on scientific
studies stuff that's already out there
but not organized and then also our data
right like what did I choose to buy
where am I going MERS which I should own
but I should also be empowered to use
that for the collective good and so to
be able to have one data one database
you can be centralized but like you're
you know I mean you don't have to
recreate the wheel you don't have to
read put in all the data for all the
products because the products can be for
the economics and you for politics and
for the environment can be for the
supply chain I mean there's a lot that
can come out of every piece of data and
the interconnectedness and so yes having
one common pool of data and then
transparency on what that's used where
it came from and what it's used for is
important and then anyone can use that I
mean that's a lot of what a lot of apps
are built on but then they have to make
their own right like how many recipe
apps are there out there I don't well I
know I want one place with recipes and I
don't want to read your life story
before I get to the recipe just want the
recipe and I want to be able to tweak it
if I want to and be able to find other
people and the taste buds like me and
they even tried this recipe and said it
was good and there's just like so much
we can do when we're sharing information
with each other and creating I think
what the design is made like the kind of
what's hidden behind the scenes all the
kind of back-end is actually made
visible to to everyone on the surface
and they're given the freedom to then
work with it customize it and tweak it
it just opens up so much possibility you
know I'm really interested in the idea
of like you know looking at the game be
community on Facebook it to me it just
feels I think probably this is like you
know common feeling amongst most people
that Facebook's framework and toolset
feels very like restricting you know
there's all these people there that have
got really interesting perspectives and
there's a huge amount of intelligence
and yeah we're kind of clashing against
each other and like a lot that could be
done isn't getting done I think and it's
I think a lot of that's down to just the
limitations the framework but if you
have this kind of open open system you
know people like myself who were doing
coding and I'm sure there's a bunch of
coders in that community to just start
developing a new tool like a new way to
filter the the news feed or like a new
polling tool or you know like something
I'm really interested in is data
visualization you know like if you could
just have access to the database of all
the different data points that have been
gathered
by Facebook you know in the game be
community and then you could visualize
that in interesting ways and customize
that and so much creativity in so much
information that could be made available
and accessible so it's just a huge
potential and I think it's inevitable
that it's going to happen but I don't
think it's going to happen through
Facebook
you know it'd be amazing surprise if it
did but I really don't see that
happening I mean Facebook isn't designed
for for us to create game via and it's
just not it's designed for profit it's
designed for Zuckerberg and shareholders
to make profit which means division and
I mean half the tough stuff I pasted not
post in facebook either in one of the
individual groups or in the game B group
itself or on even on my personal page
most of its crickets most of it and I'm
like well how much of that is because
Facebook doesn't maybe like me they they
you know grey lists you or how much is
just like what I'm writing isn't
resonating with people and so they see
it but they don't understand what's
going on or like how much they see it
not connect with it or how much are they
just not seeing it and then is it
designed for them to do anything with
anyway and so the more we can have those
conversations of like here's what's
possible if a group of people get
together what if we what if Facebook was
designed for the collective good what if
it was designed to help you find your
people instead of getting in fights with
your old high school friends and
extended family like if instead it was
designed for you know not to be in that
division because I guess them the most
money with the algorithm but instead
like oh here's more people who agree
with you not so you can be in an echo
chamber so you can actually create
something together and yeah they're just
I mean there's an infinite number of
possibilities we can do a technology
when it's created together because it's
if we have trust and we have funding and
we have the people it's all possible and
it's not like this is my one of my big
things about technology is most of the
trade-offs that exist in regular
business and regular life don't exist in
technology or they can be mitigated in
technology like the idea of like the
individual in the group it's like well
you're born into a group and you're
either part of it or you're not right
you're either like that thing and you
fit in or you don't
whereas now with the Information Age and
that you can God find your people but
it's not a given it's hard to find your
people the more we can
make that a possibility so if you don't
need to choose between the individual in
the group everyone can be an individual
and find their group they resonate with
I just can't dictate who your group is
right I can't be like everyone has to be
vegan everyone has to ride a bike
everyone it's like you ride a bike you
be vegan all you want and find your
people that are also that like real
world community or a book club or
anything that you want to build yeah
yeah that made me think as well just
like you know some of the recent
conflicts that have happened in game be
community and you know in loads of
communities you're seeing the same kind
of thing happen and there's like a
really rigid moderation structure where
basically you either in the group and
you can post everyone sees it or you're
out of the group no one can see you
within that context so it's just this
kind of black and white either in or out
and yet it wouldn't it would be so easy
to just build tools that enable of
customization where you know basically
if you know people could flag stuff as
being potentially offensive and if you
were someone you didn't like offensive
content you just go into your settings
and you just choose to hide that if you
want to see it you can see it and
suddenly like those situations that lead
to so much tension and kind of chaos
like would just be able to unfold and it
would you just wouldn't have nearly as
many of the problems and there's so many
different things like that yeah yeah one
of my friends it was I think it was two
years ago on Mother's Day she just
posted on Mother's Day it was like I
really hate Mother's Day I really wish I
didn't have to see it and was like well
how dare you it's like she wasn't saying
no one should celebrate it she's like
she doesn't want to see it and there
should be a filter for that to be able
to say listen for Christmas I'm really
triggered I don't want to see Christmas
stuff I don't want to see that because
it's like the idea of trigger warnings
is like yes they're good they're trying
to help people at the same time there
are a lot of Labor to put them in and
they only deal with the overarching
right like who's gonna put a trigger
warning on Mother's Day right like hey
mom I love you I didn't just need a
trigger warning except for her it does
it's like I have a really bad
relationship with my mom she abandoned
me and I don't want to be reminded of
that right I don't want to go on if I'm
having a bad day and so to be able to
put those filters in place that it's
your choice right to see things or not
see things and to be able to opt in or
opt out and yes the other people be like
you
we can just separate you don't need to
see you don't need to comment on
everything you don't need to see the
stuff that's going to bring up all of
this gross emotion in you yeah okay how
much about you get exposed and it
actually reminds me it's not quite the
same but kind of a parallel in politics
where you know the modern political
system it's it's the two-party system
where you end up like there's always
inevitably going to be two frontrunners
and you know you end up basically being
forced to pick between them and you you
might disagree with both of them on most
things but you're kind of forced to pick
one side and the other and it ends up
pitting populations into kind of against
each other into like two teams that are
kind of battling even though under the
surface there's a huge amount of overlap
in terms of their interests and their
differences there's way more complex but
it's that's not being recognized in that
system so you know I think there's a
huge potential for kind of like poll it
like actually that was one of the things
that initially got me into this I didn't
research from that work was just
thinking about like you know what if
there was like a global polling website
where you could just find out a global
opinion on any subject and you could
pull your views on any subject and you
know it'd be fascinating and I think it
people would actually feel more engaged
because it's sort of just choosing
between two rubbish options you could
put forward your opinions on the things
that you're passionate about and
interested in and it would count towards
something so yeah I think there's just
loads of situations like that where
we're kind of like we're in simplistic
systems that like were you know it's not
that they you know they're there for a
reason like they're you know for example
the two-party system that's great
compared to a dictatorship where there's
just one one party but it's also like
terrible compared to a system where
people could be putting all kinds of
different opinions and inputs into it so
yeah at the governance thing I mean it's
because two parties doesn't work
multiple parties is almost even worse I
think you're in a first-past-the-post as
well right it's like I don't know which
ones are both horrific but it's like we
actually could govern a country or maybe
it's village let's try with a village on
liquid democracy and yet maybe we
couldn't right because
everyone's like oh I want no taxes and I
want all the spending in the areas I
want them to be in right I want
unlimited education for my children and
unlimited healthcare for my family but I
don't want to pay for everyone else is
and I don't but it's like when you're
actually voting on things it isn't just
yes or no hopefully I mean in polling it
would be but it's it's like right then
we have a million dollars where are we
spending it you can't take it from here
without finding more of it right like
you actually do need to have each
individual sum what I'm able to
understand the the ripple effects right
like you can't just say no taxes and
high spending that doesn't work oh but
you can say hey let's all put in a
little bit more for this of this tax so
we can do this thing or be in favor of
it and maybe and this is where I think
government and politics is broken even
though I get why it's there is that like
if only the people who said yes to
military were the ones funding the
military we wouldn't have military
probably we wouldn't have and there are
things that we need that people wouldn't
fund right I don't know if people with
fund roads we need roads
right like you might not fund education
if your kid wasn't currently in
education but so there are things that
you need we need to kind of just
prioritize and say yes everyone needs
education everyone needs health care but
to be able to say okay how do we solve
healthcare education food anything for
the group of people who want to solve it
then it's a voluntary tax right it's
like oh and funny minute acts like
you're putting ten dollars into the pool
to create this solution together you
know we don't have to create solutions
for everyone so we don't have to make
everyone happy we don't even have to
make everyone in this group happy there
are there are autonomous individuals
right they can come and bring them like
kind of the worst of all worlds or we
both like we don't have a say in our
government beyond just voting and they
also can't make everyone happy so they
can't do anything and we can't do
anything so nothing's getting done
instead of like oh let's just bring a
group of citizens together pull our
money not all of our money but you know
a tiny bit of our money and then create
something together and then we can own
it together and create real actual
tangible solutions that bypass our
government and make our lives better and
then keep improving incremental II it's
like you start with the beta I keep
scared
better and eventually you know competes
Facebook and Google and eventually you
don't need governments because what are
they doing nothing because they can't
and the stuff they can do we could
probably do better together so do you
like because I'm totally sold on this
trajectory as well like I've shared
about it in communities before and like
it's such a complicated thing you can
only kind of loosely point at it and say
like there's this kind of thing and but
it's like you know it's like trying to
describe a living cell or something
there's just so many different aspects
to it it's kind of organic as well it's
not like it's not even like the Machine
you know a complicated machine it's just
so complex but do you think like like
what what kind of scale use time scale
are you thinking about like you and do
you think yeah I don't know like how how
soon do you think that this could happen
and do you think how do you reckon the
rest of the world would respond when
something like this started to gain a
bit of traction how the world responds
is a whole other question because it
could be that the media absolutely
vilifies and people are like like
constantly when I'm talking about my
vision people like that sounds like
socialism I'm like so I don't care that
it sounds like socialism I'm not against
socialism but also it's involuntary
socialism if it is right it's like so
you don't need to come and participate
so what is the problem but that doesn't
mean they won't find one it doesn't mean
like we constantly care about what our
neighbors are doing what other people
are doing wouldn't we really should it's
not affecting our lives but the time
scale wise I mean that's part of what
solution raising or we're coming up with
a solution in an hour and showcasing
what we could do with a hundred thousand
dollars and ten thousand people and then
having multiple ones so we can say hey
imagine we have the food one the
education one you know they're all just
adjacent possible they're not a utopian
vision of the future it's like hey an
online learning system that we can all
use and contribute to a food system to
know what's cheap and how to coordinate
with your neighbors whatever it is right
it's like a little thing it's the tude
still has a big impact but isn't you
know let's take down the entire
government or something all of the
little projects are something a tech
team can do and say it's six months
under six months right especially one
that had funding and $100,000 isn't that
hard to do with ten thousand he
again $10 per month you can have fun one
per month and vote on which one we want
to fund this beginning part where the
snowball is getting started and people
can't see the vision right there like
tech cooperative why it's slow and it's
arduous but once it starts rolling on
its own right once there's that social
media platform that anyone can come on
and start giving an idea to and maybe
that doesn't work cuz you can't have all
ideas at once maybe you need to start
with one idea and then work on that one
until it's done but they're all
interconnected like you need you need
your needs a minute able to concentrate
on working you need to be able to find
your people be able to make teams you
need to be able to have the information
and databases nerd field do a lot of
this stuff but also there's ways to
start from now like the idea cafe and
the solutions cooperatives are Sochi and
racing and such where once it starts I
have a completely different time frame
than everyone else cuz I'm like we can
honestly be living in in what would be
deemed utopia from this standpoint in
ten years because like I mad like we
look at technology from ten years ago
right I'm like all the phones that's
what they look like we do you really
have smartphones and and that was not
organized right it was just dealing with
capitalism and incentives and people
like they have to make stuff and then do
it in secret and sell it to us and we
don't trust them and once we have that
open system where people can see and
everyone can come and be involved and
you're dealing with like everyone can
solve their own problems right you're
empowered to solve your own you can also
leave it up to other people right like
other people created a food app you can
come and be part of it but you can't
yell at them for creating something you
didn't know they didn't know you needed
because you weren't involved
like it's like empowering people to
solve their own problems together
means that all the problems get solved
simultaneously and so if it's not a
solution for you what would make it a
solution for you what's the next
iteration how do we continually improve
it how do they connect together then
yeah ten years you have game be in ten
years like I and I get that that sounds
pie-in-the-sky but I'm like I don't know
how we don't do that like it's like we
that's why I can have hope that like
this is there like generations from now
like we don't need generations from now
we don't have generations from now we
don't need generations from now we need
the technology
because a lot of what game B is right
that we need the people to be conscious
enough to do this stuff I think is
backwards
I would love those people to exist I
want everyone to become more conscious
and care about animals and people and
but if we need them to do that first it
doesn't work we have to meet people
where they are so we have to give them
solutions that are cheaper easier
smarter than what they currently have
and we can do that together right like
we can create something much better than
Facebook together and then the beginning
part of the people who get the Facebook
it's a little evil but then eventually
it's like why would you be on Facebook
when there's this thing we all home
together that's like not only giving me
a newsfeed but like helping me feed my
family helping me find my passion
projects helping me like do my just
everything right this is like my
personal assistant and I pay $10 a month
for it yeah I can see it's saving me a
thousand yeah I'll pay for it right so
once we once it starts everything
explodes very rapidly yeah yeah I see
the same way it's like you know
technology or something you know - you
get a very long gradual curve and then
suddenly it reaches a certain threshold
and then becomes very steep and I think
that's just there's all the ingredients
are kind of like building and they're
just ready for a big change to happen
but I think that's the thing the
challenge that we've got now is to just
build those like solid foundations and
create that kind of framework around
which then once that energy you know
once people recognize it that that
energy can actually flow into it and it
can kind of like survive and grow and
expand and handle that energy because I
think the danger is like you know if say
ten thousand or a million people right
now came and we're just like you know we
love your ideas like let's do it I feel
like right now we're probably not quite
prepared to coordinate would be very
difficult but I think like you know
there was someone was saying the other
day in the game be community that it's
almost like you know there was this
really long period before the first
sales formed on earth where kind of the
ingredients were just like bubbling and
slowly coming into the right place but
then as soon as you get an actual soul
that can kind of reap
juice and survived suddenly there's a
new process just like rapidly as
triggered I feel I feel like that's
what's kind of happening and game be
like I've actually been really
interested in I mentioned this on the
call the other day like they're kind of
sub communities that started forming
within game B I think partly because
like my the social network I've been
involved in week Oh
like one of the unique features of it is
the way that communities are organized
into this kind of like holler key or
this like fractal branching structure we
have like you have a community or a
subject like science and then within
that you have like a nest nested sub
communities like physics and chemistry
because you can you can apply that kind
of structure that framework to pretty
much any conceptual domain you know like
it works in all different areas so like
you know you could have like I kind of
came to this idea from reddit so for
example like you know reddit there'll be
like a subreddit for my City Bristol and
they'll be you know subreddit for all
these different categories but there's
just one level you know you've just got
a massive space for Bristol sharing and
I thought you know it'd be so awesome if
you could within that you could have
like Bristol artists and Bristol food
you know people are interested food at
Bristol garden and then within those you
could have further subcategories that
could be created by the users and they
become kind of sharing spaces and so I
think that kind of design is like that's
maybe why I've been like particularly
interested in seeing that kind of
starting to happen and game B but I
think that's yeah see having these kind
of like areas for the different or
different spaces for sharing around the
different subjects that we're kind of
realizing our parts of this game B
system that's really valuable and I just
hope that over time the in each of those
spaces we kind of developed more clear
ideas so that as more people come in you
know the ideas are mapped out clearer
and there's more things that people can
do and yeah yeah I mean that would be
totally ideal it's what we're kind of
trying to do with the projects the
Gateway projects is bring people with
projects together to have the
conversation of like what needs to be in
place to help our projects exist because
a lot of that saying conversations
happen
under like the science umbrella where
it's like physics and actually it's
probably better to do the other one
where like Bristol has its own Vancouver
has its own I find because not
everything is in that structure right
there's also like Vancouver food might
want to talk to Bristol food especially
if we're going traveling right and so
like the interconnected circle like I'm
one node and I have a lot of aspects
right like I might want to talk to my
career community I might want to talk to
the disabled community I might want to
talk to two single moms and I'm like and
so I'm all of those things and my my um
contribution to the world is that I'm
all of those things right I'm the
connecting point to those and there's
other people would be the connecting
point but basically no one's your exact
connecting point and so there's places
where that that someone hierarchy exists
right of like science and then these
things underneath but it's also like
right but we also need to bring in art
to science right and and an economics
and like all of the inter inter
pollination but then you also kind of do
want it like you want chemistry to be
with chemistry so that if I'm
understanding chemistry I don't need a
background in history and linguistics
and all this stuff but I could write
like cuz cuz that's part of it it's like
if you have a if you have history and
chemistry awesome you bring those two
together right so being able to find
yeah just both like hierarchy and also
the interconnectedness yeah yeah I
totally agree with that and that's like
that's actually a part of the design is
that you can at least the one that we've
worked on is that you can have you know
any branch can exist and I kind of
wonder where the branch is now is like
is actually the rep the best term
because it does imply a more rigid
framework where like nodes might be you
know a better analogy but but with it
like within the design that we've
developed you can you can make basically
branches can exist in multiple locations
simultaneously and so can post as well
so when you create a post you could
target with multiple branches but you
could also like you said have a food
community that's like nested within the
city that exists in but also nested
within a wider food community so it can
be found within both of those locations
and something that's like it gets kind
of a bit abstract but like because I've
been in really interested in like
neuroscience for quite a long time I
actually think there's power
to the way that our brain thinks and the
way that information is actually
organized within our brain you know
because you could think about certain
subject and then instantly your brain
like you'll pull up different bits that
are connected from different parts of
your brain which you know and that
that's actually the way that information
seems to be organized within our brains
and so yeah like I'm kind of interested
in the idea that like I actually think
that as social networks evolve and as
our capacity like the tools increase our
capacity for collective intelligence
that will actually move towards
something that will be kind of seen as
almost like a global brain type system
that's able to kind of coordinate and
process information which can then guide
the more kind of physical aspects of our
super organism like the allocation of
resources and all those kinds of more
physical things yeah I like the idea of
leaving not leaving our resource
allocation up to AI but mostly to leave
it up to them like to some degree this
idea like the not in my backyard
principle right of like oh we need a
cool processing plan but I want to like
use that energy but I don't want the
coal processing plants in my
neighborhood and so to have people
actually vote both on yes I want it and
no I don't want it in my backyard right
and so if you do actually get a group of
people who are concentrators say yes and
yes then yeah of course you make it
there but chances are you're gonna have
people who don't want in their backyard
but they do want it to exist and finding
the algorithm it's like right we're all
saying yes to it so whoever it does
whoever we decide it goes to for pros
and cons of all the areas that's the
place it is right like it's not a judge
who can be bought or so like it's like
the data decided right algorithm of the
data and we had a discussion on what
that looks like we just didn't run it -
no wait
am i voting for it to be in my backyard
yeah you know doing doing things like
that well that that's definitely I think
an interesting area of AI is kind of not
actually having the AI kind of made the
decision but basically like taking ever
all the input from all the humans around
the world and then kind of like figuring
out what what solution satisfies the
most people's needs by kind of crunching
that data in a way that an
human just could never do so yeah that's
another area that's a huge amount
potential that it's just I mean when you
realize how much information is out
there and I don't know what point you
surpassed the one human cannot know
everything probably pretty soon as soon
as we started interconnecting with other
tribes we probably were there because
you could hold the information for your
tribe but you probably couldn't also
hold the information for someone else is
all history all science like every time
we come up with something new how many
papers are like there's millions of
hours of YouTube video uploaded every
day right like you can't know everything
when I was a kid you could actually
potentially watch everything on
television not really because things
played at the same time but like there
was a handful of shows out there you
could watch them all um you can't
there's no way if there's not and have
like you just can't there's not even
enough hours in the day and stay on top
of them even like the ones that are
aired on television let alone all the
YouTube while the Netflix and Hulu and
all of that stuff and so to be able to
create the system that honors that that
is both like right not that we need to
be watching television necessarily but
like these are the shows that you would
like and not to say we're so let's stop
let's stop making them and only make the
number that everyone can watch no it's
like we have the plethora of information
we have the plethora of silent science
it's how do we organize it and make it
accessible so that my doctor can
actually know all of human chemistry and
physics and biology and ecology in order
to be able to help me get my health
right which they don't have any of that
and I know they don't have any of that
you miss to hold them in a position of
God when they have less information than
I do like yeah no problem with that
yeah see you know this is making me
think of parallels again with like a bee
in some of these online communities
where you know in the early days it's
possible to actually read like pretty
old like check out all the posts and
read all the comments but it doesn't
take too many people to where it gets
the point where you just it's just it
gradually becomes increasingly harder
and harder to do that and then it's just
totally impossible because it's just so
much fun
and like the dynamics of like of
collective intelligence and how you
organize groups I think has to change
are those different scales and I think
that's one of the challenges that game B
is facing right now is trying to figure
out like there's a desire for it to
expand and I think everyone agrees that
that's important yeah at the same time
as it's expanding the old way that it
was organized is no longer capable of
coordinating this group and that's kind
of like frightening and problematic
because it's like the old thing is kind
of cracking and breaking in many ways
and yet there is potential for it to
kind of like evolve to a new level of
complexity and and I think that's where
this kind of frame like this kind of
fractal frame work becomes really useful
because you know if you just have one
space one container for an enormous
amount of information how do you find
your way through that content like how
do you how do you navigate that and just
typing text you know like searching by
text is helpful but I think actually
having some kind of structure where you
can be like okay I mean I'm interested
in game B but I'm particularly
interested in like psychology or
something or I'm particularly interested
in like high level systems change and
you can just quickly find the section of
gang v that's focused on that area and
then you can navigate down to a more
specific area and that you can zoom back
out when you want to and you can kind of
just navigate through all this
complexity and then again I also think
just like new tools like instead of just
being able to like stuff and being stuck
with Facebook's algorithm as to how it
ranks things you know having alternate
ways of you know labeling things maybe
allowing communities come up with custom
labels that they can apply in different
ways and then sift stuff according to
those labels or using like rating
systems or different kinds of reputation
systems and there's you know there's
just so many different ways that I think
we could navigate through this
increasing amount of data as a community
let's say the game be community we could
choose what topics have salience what
people have salience right every time
Jordan Hall posts even though he's not
there anymore I want to see his posts
right I want to see maybe I don't want
to see Jim Radford do you want to see
Jim ruts like
what what do I want to see and then but
so that's like but also me right as an
individual maybe I choose I don't want
to see Jordan Hall and I wanted I want
to see Knicks posts right so like both
as a group so that we can give more
salience to the ideas that are going to
generate this forward and and like I put
it put up a lot of ideas that are very
like let's try this is an experiment and
it puts up a lot of ones that are on
poles that are about their amazing
one-off little little tidbits and so but
then again I also post some content that
maybe isn't useful right so it's like I
want to be able to say no this one is
it's like I want people to come to the
idea cafe that's actually pretty
important especially new people who
haven't seen it before like this is a
place having one place where people can
see here's what you can be involved in
alright I think that is what makes my
project different then many other
projects out there is anyone can get
involved like this isn't my baby and no
one else can touch it it's like come
participate in the idea cafe come
participate the project raises and
solutions everything eyes design is
designed for the masses to get involved
without it being capable like you said
10,000 people knowing people coming on
board isn't feasible but luckily it
grows organically and if it doesn't part
of it's owning that piece of it like if
the four of us are on a board meeting
you call them we happen to have a
thousand people watching it isn't gonna
be very easy to have a conversation with
them in the comments but then we
introduce things like polls and things
that are like hey someone asks a
question and people upload it right like
something that is that does bring that
like yes 10,000 people can't be on a
board of directors conversation right
but there are ways to vote for the board
of directors so you can empower me or
empower Bentley or like there's ways to
to create it together where it could be
hey yes there's 10,000 people we honor
they're not ever all 10,000 people are
gonna be the ones deciding on things
we're not there yet we don't have the
infrastructure but also we don't just
let it fall away and be like well oops
10,000 people right like it's we come up
with solutions that could work for
10,000 people and then is this working
what would make it even better right so
the people drop off because they don't
feel like they're included and bones
that's a problem but you as long as
you're looking for the problems and try
to
all of them and people are empowered to
be part of the solution right like I
want from those 10,000 people to know
how do we had 10,000 people involved and
I want the best ideas to come to the to
come to the top I don't want to listen
to 10,000 people's ideas mmm
but I'll listen to five people's ideas
and everyone could listen to five
people's ideas and upload them right and
I'd do it in in ways that do that work
ish and then looking for new and better
ways to do governance and communication
and the feeling that the individual gets
how involved they are and whether
they're being heard and their ideas
listened to yeah yeah I mean it just
reminded me that again I've just you
know like I was been interested in in
reddit for quite a while just because
it's this you get these different
communities and sharing spaces for
different subjects and there's this kind
of filtering process within it where
everyone can kind of contribute and it's
kind of filtering out to the surface the
top of the stuff that's like deemed the
most relevant to that communities it's
not fixed to any specific metrics it's
just whatever is deemed most interesting
by that community but I think there's
yeah like I'm I'm fascinated and all
that kind of thing like how are these
different tools like what are the
different tools what do they what
advantages do they provide what scale
they most appropriate and how does that
fit into this larger kind of framework
of collective intelligence but I think
yeah having having feedback things as
well so if people are watching and
they're like I don't like this is there
a way that they can put that across or
if they've got a new idea can they can
they get that into the mix and then have
that filtered up and it's just like this
kind of dynamic system yeah exactly when
you're looking for thing reasons it's
breaking right it's also like I don't I
like Reddit and I don't like reading I
feel like whenever I put anything out
there it's crickets ill there too like
in the bigger ones you don't get seen
and if the first few people don't upvote
you then it's lost and you don't even
there's ways and it's okay because
everyone's kind of in the same boat but
it's like no bhaiyaji you can save the
world like I want it to be uploaded
right and there's a lot of people who
aren't great at writing are great at the
communication piece but the idea
and I think mine is yours is very
similar right like but that doesn't mean
everyone thinks it is a new idea so
doesn't people don't see the beauty in
it but like how do we those are the very
ideas we need especially for people who
don't know how to sell them and don't
know how to communicate them like I have
a hypothesis that basically every
solution exists already on this planet
right we have a solution clean up the
oceans to sequester carbon to do for
unlimited and on Janee that's super
cheap but the people who know how to do
it I have to go through the marketplace
to get it out there and it's broken like
your your it takes a lot of work and a
lot of ego killing to put yourself out
there when people can like make your
projects sound stupid or like you
already sound stupid things like it's
hard I'm willing to do it because my
project I think is so important that I'm
like I'm willing to like do this again
and again and again until it exists in
the world but not everyone is right if
my solution was only how to clean up the
ocean right like oh someone else will
take that on right like you put it out
there and you tell 100 people and
everyone's like that's not gonna work
you're not gonna keep telling people
right whereas if instead we could be
like listen ocean needs to get cleaned
up
who's got solutions and then how which
one is the best right and maybe you
didn't hear about that in the beginning
so your solution comes on later but like
who cares we have a dozen solutions on
how to clean up the ocean here's the
best one we have so far
it doesn't mean it's the end all be all
monopoly you clean it up if you have a
new idea that's better we don't start
with that because we've already gotten
so far on this one but like how do we
incorporate yours into this how do we
how do we actually get ideas into the
world without needing the person to be
the marketer the communicator yeah well
that that to me like reminds me of like
I don't think I explained it very well
earlier but like the the idea of kind of
using mapping within communities like
gaming because I think is if that is one
of the challenges with the tools that
we've got at the moment is that in
amongst that community there's loads of
people they've got different ideas or
little pieces of the puzzle but how do
you find that in the community like at
the moment there isn't a space I can go
to to see like who's got ideas on how to
fix problems with the ocean like there's
I feel like there should be a space for
every idea every kind
concept or space like that every domain
like that so if you've got an idea it
doesn't matter how developed it is it
could just be you know just something
off the top of your head you can put it
in there and then other ideas can be put
in there and they can accumulate over
time and then other people looking at
that space can go in and maybe they
could just go through and like tag one
be like oh that's a really good idea or
that one wouldn't work for this reason
and it's just adding bits of information
of that space and over time that can
accumulate and you know it reminds me a
bit of kind of just the scientific
enterprise you know that you've got all
these different branches of science and
you have people going out and doing
research and experiments on different
areas but because it's actually being
written up and kind of added to this
accumulating library of information it
means that you know ideas can evolve
beyond individuals you know someone
might contribute a little bit and then
they die and then the next generation
can come across that bit of information
do some more experiments that add on it
and then you know that that would be
their contribution and then other people
do stuff but then over generations and
generations you see this kind of
continuous evolution of all these
different branches and I kind of I think
that there's potential you know haven't
got it clearly in my head yet but I
think there's tools that could be built
like without too much difficulty that
would actually enable that kind of stuff
to be experimented with already so yeah
some like I've written a little bit
about it but it's it's a struggle to
kind of communicate these ideas to two
groups because like you said like some
of these ideas like for me to kind of
really put them into writing they end up
being pretty long essays which take ages
to do and then is really intimidating
and most people don't want to read
through all that kind of stuff but how
do you communicate it and that's where I
mean I think there's a handful of
projects that if they existed already
would be huge game changing overnight
like having one social media platform
that we owned together that even if it's
in the most beta form if we're looking
to improve it and create it better that
is what we want we want something that
is and then talking about databases at
all that's like some where anyone can go
and find a project and work on
project right even if it's just now
let's have a second conversation about
what that actually looks like and it
builds into that all the tools we need
the scheduler the project management
system right whatever we need organized
whatever is gonna be the most bang for
about to be in this and then one of
those things is also like a solution
like a Yelp for solutions like something
that is both the the tech space itself
right what apps exist in this space what
are their features what are common what
aren't how much does it cost to
comparison an actual comparison that is
in Google or Android itself one to five
stars like what it's actually there and
if we were to create something what
would we clearly wanted to be the best
of all of them right but also just
solutions in general right what
solutions exist in food right what 3d
farming and any new gadget that comes
out what is it used for and does it how
long does it last how long like actual
metrics to know the things we want to
know about a product or service or and
then getting that database right that
isn't Yelp owning it because again Yelp
has its own incentives to not
necessarily tell you the truth to listen
to their restaurants and you can pay for
better reviews and you can pay to get
bad reviews taken down and then we start
trusting it and they stop having
credibility so finding ways that are how
do we share information how do we create
these databases that are that we trust
right there because any of the
world-changing projects that they're
one-off then they have to go through all
of the problems everything else does
right design the Yelp for solutions are
people going to use it they're looking
to input information or people gonna
trust it or people gonna like and that's
where like for me I'm focused more on
like bringing the community together but
there already is right there's already
the game being community there's already
these people but like there's also like
the Facebook group that we started a
couple weeks ago that the project crazy
and it's still just basically Bentley me
and Adriel and somewhat Ricci posting
right like it's like okay how do we
which is fine but like how do we get
into the conversation of why what making
posts what gets you here what how do we
get the matter project of projects
what's what does it need to offer you
what what does bring the individual and
the project together and keep having the
conversations of like what's working
what's not working and how do we improve
it and I don't mean
hmm I'm not approving anything unless it
like spontaneously happens through me
that's kind of my my job if I love it if
I want to do it and it's enjoyable and
easy that's what I do and it's working
but other people don't like that in fact
I really think I triggered one of the
game B people last week when he was he
was like just going discard I was art
he'd send me something on discord and I
was like uh here's better on Facebook he
was like oh we'll just watch this video
on how to use discord I'm like I'm not
using discord unless I can log in with
Google on Facebook he's like it's so
disappointing that you see that because
you're trying to create the tech thing
I'm like I know but we don't own discord
so it's not like it's it's the worst of
both worlds it's not user friendly and I
can't even I have like five different
accounts at this point in time because
every time someone sends me a discord
link and like it gives me a new account
like this is not solution it's not tech
friendly and it's like to be able to do
these things
oh that like we all want everyone to
have the information we have right like
read this thing read watch this
documentary because I because it spoke
so much to me like right but then I'm bu
like I'm my node of information it's
actually okay to not read things you
don't want to read you don't watch
things you don't want to watch just do
your piece right like what what is your
area of expertise or not want to use of
your area of interest and then following
following that path and it does not come
off well though like I'm not reading
anymore
well like you can't not read it like no
I can I can absolutely refuse to real
like part of it is I have no choice my
brain wouldn't let me read I just get
really exhausted but now I've passed
that now I'm at like in it has to be
such an amazing book for me to be
willing to get through the fatigue of
reading it that that bar is so high it's
not happening because someone's like
read this book like I used to read four
books a week I'm not there anymore and I
don't need to be I'm good
I'm saving the world with where I'm at
and let you read that book tell me the
information you hold that information
yeah I think I think that's completely
fair enough and it's just one of the
things that's good that everyone's so
different you know like he was making me
think that if I think recently I heard
Jim Wright saying that like he hates
face-to-face chats that loves to read
stuff like that's just you know every I
guess
everyone's different and you kind of
want that variety I think that's really
really important and you want that kind
of range of tools so that everyone can
find things the way that it suits them
matches them yeah I've many of YouTube
videos that treat me like I'm a
kindergartner like the little cartoon
ones explain something to me I'm like
that's the level I need an ad is that
not available but I'm sorry I can't read
the book as like an intro because like
you know not time you want to at least
get a quick summary of what you're
getting into and then I'll know if I
want to invest more time right and that
like not everyone is gonna make a cute
little intro video that's gonna work for
you know it's gonna keep my entertaining
to keep my attention or anyone's
but even not like we could actually put
out to if how many people you know we
had a million people on a social media
platform or like hey no one's done that
for the biochemistry right no one's done
that for this piece of it and then it's
like you know that that needs to get
doesn't need to get done but it could
get done right so then if you're someone
who both can make video in like
chemistry like oh I can do that piece
right it's like finding the tasks for
the person and also being the person
who's like I need this right I want this
task done it doesn't mean it's gonna get
done if you can't do it it's not
necessarily gonna get done but it can
get put it out into the universe and if
it's catalogues correctly the right
people will find it
yeah well this this is actually one of
the tools that I think would be I don't
know if it sounds like some of the stuff
you thought of together tech might align
with this but I think a tool that would
be really useful for the game be
community is something that would like I
don't have you use something like Trello
or yeah a little bit basically you can
just create a little like note which is
just like a task that needs to be
completed and then you can like move it
through different stages so you could
have it in the backlog you could be like
an active task and then a completed task
is just like a really basic way of
organizing stuff and then you know like
for in-game be it would be cool if like
you know people could just create tasks
that they're like you know it'd be
awesome if someone did this and then
other people just browse them and then
if there's you know if you happen to
have the skills or the ability to
contribute to one of those
you can get it get it complete and then
you know they could like I think at
least initially people would some people
would still we motivate to do it even if
there was no reward or incentive but
there can also be ways of incentivizing
that too and that might just help to
coordinate things and help your
community to kind of get things done
more effectively
you know project management and task
management I mean there's a lot of
really cool tools out there like Trello
I'm sure Monday comm all the ones they
keep advertising me cuz I keep clicking
on them but they're all astronomically
expensive for someone who doesn't have
money and it's like because it's like
five bucks a month per person per month
I'm like yeah so if I want 10,000 people
you're like that's like that's not
feasible and of course we're not there
yet we don't have 10,000 but the point
is like all of those things are the
things we kind of need to recreate
because once you gets even hundred
people they start being astronomically
expensive it's not just one tool you
need all of these tools then how do they
interconnect but when even Google comes
out with something like that on the
Google Drive for free or like it's like
that will explode everything and so I
just say we should create it like we
should create the thing that is the task
management and ideally that's where
project game B projects goes is we
figure out our pain points that we all
have our individual projects and we
create the thing the task system that
helps us do that and in turn in turn
give each other gifts right like I'm
like hey I know marketing Alex Jake I
know finance I can sit with you and have
that conversation I maybe know I don't
necessarily have a skill set that I'm
the best and any of those things but I
can sit and have a conversation with
anyone I can be part of a team to like
help you raise your project right to
find the pick the problems with it and
help you you might have to solve them
but I can also think of solutions for
other people's problems more easily they
can pick up for my own and just work
through like what what's stopping you
right now for moving your project
forward or your idea forward right and a
lot of its like I don't have the people
I don't have the skills to do this I
don't have the money I don't have the
grade like as long as we can be Onis
open and honest about those things that
we can create solutions that are like
all of them right like we all don't have
funding depends what
mean if you mean you want $5,000 a month
under the pool to pay your salary no
we're not solving that yet but if we you
know what I mean we're all using Trello
and we won't you know name you know we
want to like maybe fund that that's a
difference right and it's like well
who's gonna be finding how do we get the
cheapest how do we get the best stuff
for what we got in my brain I could feel
it like shutting down probably go pretty
stupid couldn't go up an app but yeah
you know I probably aside I've seen but
yeah I think like just a last point is I
think I see the the kind of one of the
key next steps is getting that kind of
like seed social networking place with
the kind of the most basic functionality
that would provide real use to people
and that's something that I'm kind of
working on in my free time and my free
time is pretty limited at the moment but
my goal at the moment is kind of by the
end of the summer to have recreated most
of the functionality that's on week at
the moment I can send you a link to that
if you're interested in checking it out
but yeah I'm really interested in like
especially people like yourself you were
thinking about these kinds of things in
just figuring out like what would be
those key features that you would need
to make it really useful at that early
stage so yeah I'll share up like yeah
when I get a chance I'll send over a
little bit more information about kind
of the basics of what I'm trying to put
together but if you've got ideas on like
just some little features that would be
really useful to you guys with together
tech like yeah that would be helpful to
me to know that Calista totally down
with giving that information to everyone
in anyone it's like you're Zoe needs
yard to be able to work through and if
we can even come up with it but like to
me there's so many people in game B who
are coming just in game B we're coming
up with collaboration platforms yeah and
those are important but this and I think
they are fundamental but the issue is
because they're all fractured like all
of them are kind of beta and they're not
our beta right like it's like someone's
version that usually doesn't have enough
time or enough money or enough user
friendliness to actually like get to the
next level it's like if we could come
together instead of it being practice or
ium or wiko or i can never remember what
you know this one one is having it be
like here are the features we all need
it to be right and then if you're the
person knows how to code
awesome how do we get you paid for that
that's a lot of work but like what is
what would game be need for this right
and there's only a thousand people in
the Facebook group but so that's kind of
too small to fund it because you know be
like tens of thousands of dollars
probably to create a decent one if not a
hundred thousand dollars but especially
if you can talk to other people you know
in similar projects and have like what
do we need one of the features we need
to be able to work through our
individual projects and that's where the
meta project is more so if you want to
bring your project to the matter project
that might be a very powerful cuz you
already working on it and if it becomes
the thing that we can put our projects
on and be able to work through our
projects then that's the social media
platform we need right to be able to say
hey how do we find out maybe we can
finance it through here but that might
be the next generation right or how do
we but for me for my opinion the person
who will be the person who creates the
the social media platform that we all
kind of Qing can use will be someone
who's willing to have it be a group
project right willing to have other
people that like they don't physically
own it and finance but that's less
important and like intellectually owning
it right like and it's hard because you
can't have people dictating to you what
you're making either right like well
this is what it needs to have it's like
that's passing off by I can't make it
though so I need other people to make it
but if collectively can decide on the
the all the features that could have
right like the best feature is this is
awesome this is like our utopian app and
then figure out well how complex is each
one how much money does each one cost
and what's the priority of each one
right and then how much can we fund with
$10,000 right and can we get 10,000 lb
like whatever that that is to be able to
then create the beta that we're all
willing to go into and try even though
it might not work to be able to help
make it better is I for me anyway the
process that I want to go through
because it's like then it's ours right
and we can build on it you can get add
to it and but yet right now with the
projects it's very no one's giving up
ownership of their project right like
we're not at that stage we're not
happened like the more someone's willing
to say here is when I'm willing to write
and don't hold me to that it's not a
legal contract but like hey when there's
10,000 people on board and everyone's
putting $10 in yes I'm willing to that
right or like whatever
that that level is or when there's five
people involved right Emily to share
with those five people whatever that was
those those kind of things are yeah I
mean I think it can start right from the
from the beginning level like you know
that's kind of the approach we've had we
chose that we you know it's we basically
said anyone's welcome to become a member
you know anyone could be a user for free
if you want to become a member it's like
you know three dollars a month and then
you can vote and you can put forward
ideas and if it's if an idea is voted on
by the majority of their members then it
basically becomes the new priority for
what's acted on
yeah I think I agree with everything
you're saying like I think there's like
watching a lot of these different
projects that are kind of there in the
game be space and I'm pretty sure that
like a little while ago I kind of made a
suggestion and tagged a bunch of people
who were in these different projects and
saying like maybe what we need to do is
is just get all these people together
somehow like I don't know what the
format would be and try and have some
kind of a public debate or discussion
around like what are the key features
that need it and how can we coordinate
to do that but I think it's very
difficult to actually do that I didn't
get a huge amount response from that
which is kind of like expect but quads I
try to have a conversation about a
conversation and nobody wants to come to
a conversation about a conversation and
it's like that one governance and
everything as well but at the same time
it has to happen like it's like if you
have a project you want to get off the
ground you have to be willing to have
conversations about your project if
you're willing to like intermix with
other people and cross pollinate and
find ways that what are the pain points
if you're willing to be vulnerable and
share what you don't know and share what
what isn't happening for you so we can
create an including things like hey
we're across 24 time zones where you
know geographically dispersed how do we
create a conversation that happens I
have solutions some solutions for that
but even that gets crickets right it's
like oh well people don't want to come
be part of a conversation that's a 24
hours on zoom' okay cool
interesting this other person is doing
it though and that seems to be working
that like there are ways to have a
continual conversation one day
we can have like six different time
slots and hey come on have that
conversation of your project and then we
have one place to keep note so we can
see what we all said was in common that
we wanted in a social media project but
even like today we had the idea cafe for
projects and it was just me and my
brother right we were talking about
trust this Trust is something we need in
place for all of the projects how do you
trust a company right what do you need
there to be in order for you to want to
download it in order for you to want to
actually put your information on it
and we couldn't really have that
conversation because we've had that
conversation so often the two of us
having it is kind of like a little bit
pointless but we did we have thing but
like them if there were eight people on
that conversation if we were able to be
like yes bring wiki lection bring
reasons for and what the name of yours
is the new week o to it right and say
what is it you need for it right - both
like it's nebulous because you're both
like you and you're holding your project
and you're also wanting this like game
be here together tech entity to also be
there but you're also dealing with all
of the emotions that that interplay is
right the ego and the ownership and
olive but like yes that's the best bit
that we kind of have to come together
and work out as well is all of that and
the more we're willing to do that but we
can't do that if people aren't there
aren't willing to have the conversations
well yeah I'll try and participate where
I can like it was cool to see in the
last school that was like seven or so
people the lot was at the last rule and
I go on oh yeah yeah Eric's thing you
know I'm just cool yeah cuz people are
allowed to just show up and have a chat
and be like you ask questions I like
that
which is I mean I don't know if you were
in the game B space in September when
the zoom call happens and the the cafe
started I wasn't watching those videos
at that point but I've kind of been I
think I was in the game B community I
think or I've been kind of just
following a lot of those thinkers anyway
so yeah I'm a really exact point I
joined the Facebook group yeah September
13th because it was also the same day
was Friday that there's some temper xiii
and there was like a big huge assume
call and Remzi told me about it like
five
before it happened I jumped on board the
first attack it was it was that there
was like a zoom cafe that anyone could
pop into it anytime and he'd randomly go
into but after about a week of that
chance of running into somebody there
was very small but it's like yeah anyway
there's lots of potential for like we
can coordinate video chat across time
zones and have it be that like our
conversation is into one off and you
don't need to listen to it or watch it
in order for the next person to be able
to add on to it I I did have a vision
for that which I can share with you
another time because I think we both
probably need to go but on how like it
was it came on this citizen assembly
from extinction rebellion I'm like why
don't we just do that but we just
created like they're like no we have to
go through our government I'm like or we
could just come together and start
talking about climate change like how do
we actually create solutions and not
need to go through that process and so I
developed a way of like every four hours
so there were like six and in per day
you'd go on and answer a question and a
group and then the next day if those who
wanted to who participated come on and
like harvest that conversation right
because they would have participated in
multiple ones over the course of the day
could come on and say what they learnt
and what happened and kind of
consolidate the notes and then you do
not like you just build on and build on
right where every every week you have a
couple questions you're answering and
you get to show up and have a
conversation with whoever's there and as
a collective bigger group we're having a
bigger conversation and we're all like
notes for that there has to be something
that comes out of it like a project or
no it's something that continues on and
that's part of like the harvesting and
just having that as part of the
conversation hey we've been having a
conversation for two months and
nothing's happens how do we get the
Trello for us right like how do we
actually create the tasks how do we
actually create the social media but
things are coming together good sadness
are you are you able to come to the
solution raising tomorrow
no I'm going to this weekend there's
actually a really cool event in Bristol
called Bristol transformed whether it's
just over the weekend there's loads of
different talks on on interesting
subjects so I'm going to have my
girlfriend and that's yeah looking
forward to that but yeah I think like
generally in the evenings I can't say
that probably be some point next week
when one evening when I'm free otherwise
generally weekends I'm free look I think
this weekend it's a 2p on the next one
it's back at 9 a.m. I believe which
would be whatever time your time hey
camera brother you're like it hours
ahead that is 7 no 6 6 p.m. the other
ones like a 10 p.m. your time or
something that's a little early what
other people's minds don't turn off at 2
p.m. so they can participate in
conversations persons that's probably
when I operate the best
yeah I've also at some point I might
post I was thinking about posting some
of the the ideas around like the week oh
projects in the in the game be projects
just absolutely that's what it's there
for
really it's like post post things all
right I'm gonna end the broadcast so we
can stop recording and I'm weekend take
my